All
right, this time I think we're on.
No, I'm not gonna I don't know my my understanding is without
the microphone nobody can hear anyway.
So I'm not gonna...
use the audio recorder though.
Right, but to try to I don't know if they're synced up
or anything like that so so if they're not then I don't
know if there's any point. Rabbi Linzer will get the the mic
that he uses normally. I don't know where to look for it.
Okay,
we finished yesterday we were talking about a variety of cases of
illegal marriages or not just illegal marriages but of a variety of
situations where it's questionable whether or not a daughter would get מזונות.
mezonot. And the last one we did was the case of שניות,
shneiyot, women who are אסורות asurot to get married דרבנן. derabbanan.
And the answer that we gave was that or what we suggested
is that perhaps the because the mother was being punished for her
behavior doesn't mean that the daughter should be punished. But at the
end of the day we said תיקו teiku we don't actually know
what the solution to that is.
So we are on נ"ד עמוד א' nundaled amud aleph one two
three four lines from the top. בעי רבא. Ba'ei Rava. בת ארוסה
יש לה מזונות או אין לה מזונות. Bat arusah yesh lah mezonot
o ein lah mezonot. The daughter of a woman who is engaged
and I have to assume that they were behaving in the in
the way of נשי יהודה nishei Yehuda as opposed to נשי גליל
nishei Galil where it seems that they had intimacy even previous to
the wedding.
A daughter of a woman who was only engaged but not yet
fully married does she get מזונות mezonot or not? כיון דאית לה
כתובה אית לה. Keivan de-it lah ketubah it lah. Maybe because this
woman who has who's engaged still has the right to a כתובה
ketubah so if the כתובה ketubah is in place maybe the תנאי
כתובה tnai ketubah are in place including the מזונות mezonot for daughters.
או דילמא כיון דלא תקינו רבנן כתובה עד שעת נישואין לית לה.
Odilma keivan de-la takinu rabanan ketubah ad sh'at nisuin leit lah. Or
maybe because the Rabbis didn't demand that there must be a כתובה
ketubah until the the time of the actual נישואין nisuin not just
the אירוסין erusin she maybe this daughter doesn't have it because we
didn't she didn't reach that moment and we leave it with
תיקו. teiku. בעי רב פפא.
Ba'ei Rav Papa. אמורא Amora תיקו. teiku.
Sorry. The previous ones were תנא Tanna תיקו. teiku.
The
ones we ended yesterday.
בעי רבא. Ba'ei Rava. The last one we did was בעי רבי
אלעזר. Ba'ei Rabbi Elazar. רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar is an אמורא. Amora.
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish is also an אמורא. Amora. So we're in
the world of the אמוראים Amoraim right now. Okay. בעי רב פפא.
Ba'ei Rav Papa. We're back in בבל. Bavel. I don't know if
anybody's keeping track of the geography of these things. We're back in
בבל. Bavel. רב פפא Rav Papa says בת אנוסה יש לה מזונות
או אין לה מזונות. Bat anusah yesh lah mezonot o ein lah
mezonot. A woman who is a daughter of a woman who is
married to her husband on account of being raped. This is a
דאורייתא de-oraita case or rather a case from the Torah. A man
who rapes a woman has to pay a certain penalty rapes an
unmarried young woman has to pay a certain penalty and then he
has to marry her and he's not allowed to divorce her.
So the question is her daughter what's the state of her daughter
because we don't we're not sure what exactly the state of the
כתובה ketubah is. The כתובה ketubah is supposed to is there as
a protection so that a man will have in mind that it's
not so easy to divorce his wife he's actually going to have
to pay some pay some money out of his pocket. This man
doesn't have the right of divorce at all. That being the case
maybe the כתובה ketubah is is of a lesser standard and maybe
then the תנאי כתובה tnai ketubah the תנאי מזונות tnai mezonot also
is a problem.
Why would that be? He's going to die. It's possible he could
die he predecease her.
So it it depends what the how you understand a כתובה. ketubah.
If you understand a כתובה ketubah as a protection
then you you'd understand that the כתובה ketubah would still be in
place. If you understand the כתובה ketubah as a counter-motivator so that
people don't just get divorced on the drop of a hat
then maybe you'd still think that we'll see that in a few
minutes I mean in a few lines they're going to bring this
up. I think what you said yesterday which is that the כתובה
ketubah ends up having stacked on top of it a whole variety
of of issues which brings up I mean reminds us also of
the case of the קנס, knas, right? Okay just because the mother
is being punished her תנאים tnaim may not kick in but that
doesn't mean that later תנאים tnaim that are protections for other people
might kick in. אליבא
דרבי יוסי ברבי יהודה
לא תיבעי לך.
aliba d'Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda
lo tiba'i lakh.
According to רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda we don't
have to ask why? דאמר יש לה כתובה כתובת מנה. De-amar yesh
lah ketubah ketubat maneh.
Because he says that she has a כתובה ketubah of a מנה.
maneh. 100 like any woman who gets married as a non-virgin. כי
תיבעי לך אליבא דרבנן, Ki tiba lach aliba d'rabbanan, but there's a
מחלוקת machloket between רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yossi b'Rabbi Yehuda and
the רבנן rabbanan דאמרי יצא כסף קנסה בכתובתה de-amri yatza kesef knassa
b'khutubtah who say the
the money that he paid upfront is essentially the money that is
in position is that's in position to be to be her protections.
Doesn't that money go to the father?
The money does go to the father, but
how does how does that protect her?
We presume again that this is a this gets back to the
question of like who how many protections do you need? We presume
that the father is in position to protect her. I'll I will
say that I'm adding into the גמרא Gemara I'm adding into the
גמרא Gemara
that it's a protection. At the end of the day all Rabbi
all the רבנן rabbanan would say is you can't make him pay
so many times. He's paid his money upfront. That will count as
as her כתובה. ketubah. Whether or not the father chooses to use
that as a protection or whether he chooses to spend it on
his own, I there's it doesn't seem to me that it's legislated
that he must. מה? Mah?
So what do we do according to the רבנן? rabbanan? כיוון דלית
לה כתובה לית לה מזוני. keivan d'leit lah ketubah leit lah mezonei.
If she doesn't have a כתובה, ketubah, maybe she doesn't get any
the daughter doesn't get any kind of מזונות. mezonot. או דילמא כתובה
טעמא מאי כדי שלא תהא קלה בעיניו להוציאה? O dilma ketubah ta'ama
mai kedei shelo tehei kalah be'einav l'hotzia?
Maybe the purpose of the כתובה, ketubah, that is to say the
purpose of the כתובה ketubah that the mother does not receive, is
because so that she won't be easy to divorce. והא לא מצי
מפיק לה. V'ha lo matzi mapik lah. And this man is not
able to give her away. However, that does not determine that means
those parts of the כתובה ketubah that are about שלא יהא קלה
להוציא shelo yehei kalah l'hotzi that שלא תהא קלה להוציא shelo tehei
kalah l'hotzi
that he shouldn't be easy to divorce, those parts are null and
void but the other תנאי tnai which are there for other reasons
still are still in play. And we say תיקו. teiku. We just
don't know the answer. We
have worked to the
now we have a פיסקא piska from the משנה, Mishnah, a quote
from the משנה Mishnah from the next תנאי כתובה. tnai ketubah. את
תהא יתבא בביתי וכולי. At tehei yatva b'veiti v'chulei.
You will sit in my house all the days of that you're
a of your widowhood and we yeah
okay we'll leave it at that because we're going to get to
the question of who held what in various places. תני רב יוסף.
Tani Rav Yosef.
רב יוסף Rav Yosef had a tradition at I've talked mentioned this
a few times, I mentioned it last maybe on Friday that רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan seems to get traditions from רבי שמעון בר יוחאי.
Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai.
It's does not clear. רב יוסף Rav Yosef is one of the
few אמוראים Amoraim that we have quite a few statements תני רב
יוסף. tani Rav Yosef. רב יוסף Rav Yosef seems to have had
an independent set of ברייתות braitot that he himself remembers from being
taught and I'm not sure what the source is, but I don't
know of anyone else who we say, you know, תני רבא tani
Rava or something like that. In any case, it says you will
be you will sit in my house and receive מזונות mezonot all
the days of your widowhood. So רב יוסף Rav Yosef says בביתי
ולא בביקתי. b'veiti v'lo b'vikati. In my house but not in my
shack, meaning there has to be a house, there has to be
space for this woman to be to sit. אבל מזוני אית לה.
Aval mezonei it lah. Even if there's if there's not space, she's
going to have to go somewhere else, presumably back to her father's
house, however she still is entitled to מזונות. mezonot. מר בר רב
אשי Mar bar Rav Ashi אמר amar אפילו מזוני נמי לית לה.
afilu mezonei nami leit lah. מר בר רב אשי Mar bar Rav
Ashi says even מזונות mezonot if there's not space in the house
that suggests there's also not resources for for this woman and therefore
this תנאי כתובה tnai ketubah doesn't doesn't come into effect. ולית הלכתא
כמר בר רב אשי, V'leit hilchata k'Mar bar Rav Ashi, but we
don't hold like מר בר רב אשי. Mar bar Rav Ashi. We
hold that although she doesn't have the house is not there's not
enough space she still does have מזונות. mezonot. Charlie.
מר בר רב אשי Mar bar Rav Ashi is the last generation
of אמוראים. Amoraim.
Yes, that is the end.
And yet they're ruling against him.
You mean הלכתא כבתראי. hilchata k'batrai. Except for that the people who
say הלכתא hilchata are a later generation than מר בר רב אשי.
Mar bar Rav Ashi.
They may have a tradition.
Yes, it's surprising that but but in the גמרא Gemara itself we
do have places where they say, you know, לאו הלכתא כ lav
hilchata k and they rule against the later later ruling.
I just got a question about the תיקו. teiku.
So ostensibly as it were there are two possible אוקימתות ukimtas as
the תיקו teiku is two possible. So להלכה l'halacha
the later authorities feel free to draw on either one of the
two possibilities as they might see fit whenever there's a תיקו? teiku?
That's a good question. I'm just looking at these at the different
where the עין משפט Ein Mishpat marks that that the הלכה halacha
and it appears that cert that certain sides of the תיקו teiku
do seem to be. to be selected, my expectation is that the
same rules of תיקו teiku would apply, the same rules of פסקנינג
paskening a תיקו teiku would apply to any kind of of ספק
safek which means ספק דאורייתא safek de-oraita would be לחומרא, lechumra, ספק
דרבנן safek de-rabbanan would be לקולא, lekula, but I honestly don't know
the full answer to that.
Thank you. אמר רב נחמן אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Nachman amar Shmuel,
תבועוה להינשא ונתפייסה אין לה מזונות. tavu'ah lehinasei v'nitpaisah ein lah mezonot.
Interesting case. The woman has lost her husband. She's now living on
the buck of the heirs, of the יתומים. yetomim. And now a
man comes forward, a paramour comes forward and proposes to her that
they go and get married, and she says no,
I can't do it, I'm not interested. Does she still, is she
still entitled to to live on the buck of the orphans? In
other words,
is she still considered to be living in full widowhood once people
are ready to get married to her but she's not ready to
get married to them?
So, does she have to take the first proposal according to this?
So that's that's difficult, right? It appears that שמואל Shmuel would say
here that yes, she has to take the, you know, if somebody
comes, or she doesn't have to take it, she just has to
know that once she has rejected a proposal, she no she'll have
to now start living on her own buck. She can't continue living
on her ex-husband's buck, her her late husband.
How do you translate נתפייסה? nitpaisah?
נתפייסה nitpaisah is she was appeased, meaning that she agreed to get
married.
She agreed to get married.
Oh, I'm sorry, did I I read it the other way. I'm
sorry, excuse me. Yes, you're right because later on it's going to
discuss it. Let's try one more time. אמר רב נחמן Amar Rav
Nachman אמר שמואל, Amar Shmuel, תבועוה להינשא ונתפייסה tavu'ah lehinasei v'nitpaisah and
she agreed to get married, אין לה מזונות. ein lah mezonot. If
she gets married, she doesn't have מזונות. mezonot. הא לא נתפייסה, Ha
lo nitpaisah, if she doesn't get
if she doesn't agree, יש לה מזונות. yesh lah mezonot. This is
where I started to this is where the where I I skipped
ahead in my mind. Right, if she doesn't agree, what then she
doesn't then she does have מזונות? mezonot? אמר רב ענאן, Amar Rav
Anan, right the גמרא Gemara is surprised by this. What, she should,
you know, and she has she's moved on.
אמר רב ענאן, Amar Rav Anan, לדידי מפרשא לי מיניה דמר שמואל,
ledidi mefarsha li minei d'mar Shmuel, I can tell you what שמואל
Shmuel meant to say. אמרה מחמת פלוני בעלי, Amrah machamat ploni ba'ali,
יש לה מזונות. yesh lah mezonot. If she says the reason I
can't get married to you is because you're not it's not לכבוד
lichvod of פלוני בעלי, ploni ba'ali, I'm still honoring his memory, then
she's still considered to be in her widowhood and and יש לה
מזונות. yesh lah mezonot. מחמת בני אדם שאינם מהוגנים לה, Machamat bnei
adam she'einam mehuganim lah, אין לה מזונות. ein lah mezonot. If it's
because you're not classy enough for her, then then she doesn't have
מזונות. mezonot.
You think that that's sort of,
you know, one type of the other? In other words, you're not
good enough for me because my husband's so much better, you know?
So I so it would appear to be that מחמת פלוני בעלי
machamat ploni ba'ali sounds to me like what you just said, which
is I'm still attached to the memory of my husband either because
I'm doing it לכבוד המת, lichvod hamet, that like I'm just not
ready to get married yet, I'm
still I'm still mourning my husband, or what, you think you can
you can compare with with my husband יוסקה? Yoske? יוסקה Yoske was
a great man, you're a שלוב. schlub. Right? Both of those would
appear to me to be מחמת פלוני בעלי machamat ploni ba'ali as
opposed to I am the daughter of so-and-so
of certain class, there was a fellow Brian yesterday who was concerned
about the class nature of marriage, but I mean marriage is often
about that,
what makes you think that, you know, what makes you think that
that you belong you're in my class?
What do you mean שאינם מהוגנים לה, she'einam mehuganim lah, I mean
class but not like they're bad guys. Or like, you know, let's
say they're degenerates or like, you know, bums off the street. I
mean, we're not expecting her to like, you know, I don't know.
I would suspect that if she has a good reason, I suspect
that like, you know, they're criminal of some if they're a criminal
or or any of the reasons that we talk about that a
woman can, you know, refuse to or get out of a marriage
and so on for those things, I imagine that they are probably
out. However, at least from the base on the basis of this,
it sounds like just about anyone who proposes marriage and the reason
she doesn't want to get married to them is because they somehow
are out she is out of their league,
that is not a reasonable claim to then continue living on the
מזונות mezonot of the of the ex-husband. It's only if it's לכבוד
המת. lichvod hamet. Those are the things that allow her to continue.
But that's only also once she accepted a proposal, even let's say
she's making herself
out on the market, then she could still get. So we're going
to talk about the market in a few minute in actually one
second.
Can I just explain? Yes. Did she receive her
hundred?
We'll talk, that's also going to, that's also coming up, we'll talk
about it, okay? אמר רב חסדא Amar Rav Chisda זנתה
אין לה מזונות. Zanta ein lah mezonos. Rav Chisda says if she
goes out and has a one-night stand, that's it, her מזונות mezonos
are over.
אמר רב יוסף Amar Rav Yosef כחלה ופרכסה אין לה מזונות. Kichla
ufirkesa ein lah mezonos. If she starts prettying dolling herself up, putting
on makeup and and nice clothing and trying to sort of and
as as Michael said, signing up for dating websites, אין לה מזונות,
ein lah mezonos, that's good enough.
But she's not getting married. Never mind, never mind.
So that's exactly the point, right? Is that so
is that because she is now on her way to trying to
get married, that indicates that she is sort of moved past living
in her husband's house. What's that?
Even if she starves?
Again, the question of sociology...
But that's why she has the כתובה, kesuvah, right? Perhaps, so she
can, you know, pass herself off.
Perhaps, so we'll get to the we'll get to the כתובה kesuvah
in one second. So we say, so I don't know, this is
an interesting level of prioritization that comes next.
מאן דאמר זנתה כל שכן כחלה ופרכסה. Man de'amar zanta kol sheken
kichla ufirkesa. The one who says she loses מזונות mezonos if she
goes out and has a one-night stand,
that's all the more so if she starts kind of making herself
beautiful in order to attract men.
מאן דאמר כחלה ופרכסה, Man de'amar kichla ufirkesa, but someone who says
that she beautifies herself, that's the case where she doesn't have מזונות,
mezonos, אבל זנתה אית לה. aval zanta is lah. But if she
just if she goes out and has a one-night stand, she still
gets מזונות. mezonos. מאי טעמא יצר אנסה. Mai ta'ama yetzer ansa. The
she had an attack of יצר הרע, yetzer hara, but it doesn't
represent a kind of willingness to go out. I have to say
it's it's either an extremely sensitive text in terms of understanding how
people have like just how sort of get impulsive, especially with regard
to
sexual
sexual behavior at various times,
or it takes a very very strong stance in terms of what
it means to start beautifying oneself and putting yourself on the market
as as Michael said. ולא היא
הלכתא ככל הני שמעתתא. Velo hi hilchasa k'chol hani shema'tata. And the
הלכה halacha is not like any of these statements we've seen until
now. אלא כי הא דאמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל. Ella ki ha
de'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel. Rather the הלכה halacha is like a
tradition of רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, which is
interesting. Hold on a second. Oh, last one was רב נחמן אמר
שמואל. Rav Nachman amar Shmuel. The תוספות Tosafot asks, how can you
have אמר שמואל amar Shmuel and אמר שמואל amar Shmuel and say
one of them is not הלכה halacha and the second one is?
But it could be that it's a difference of tradition. In any
case, the הלכה halacha is like a tradition of רב יהודה אמר
שמואל. Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel. התובעת כתובתה בבית דין אין לה מזונות.
Hatova'at kesuvata beveit din ein lah mezonos.
A woman who has gone to בית דין Beit Din and demanded
her כתובה, kesuvah, that's the end of her מזונות. mezonos. So at
this point we're talking about her hundred and 200, but also whatever
else for...
But she can still be beautifying herself as long as she doesn't
go on
a date, as long as she doesn't go to court? So that's
according to this last tradition. I'm not sure what the earlier tradition
would have said.
ולא, Velo, says the גמרא, Gemara, why she doesn't get any more
that? Sorry, and and the הלכה halacha is not like is that's
the only time when she only has when she doesn't get
מזונות. mezonos. והתניא, Vehatanya, מכרה כתובתה ומשכנה כתובתה עשתה כתובתה אפותיקי לאחר
אין לה מזונות. Machra kesuvata umishkena kesuvata asta kesuvata apotiki le'acher ein
lah mezonos.
I'm sorry, I explained it wrong.
What? And she doesn't get מזונות mezonos after she's been תובעת כתובה?
tova'at kesuva? We have a ברייתא Braita which gives the cases where
she doesn't get מזונות. mezonos. What are they? If she sold her
כתובה. kesuvah. Interestingly, it appears that we just had that discussion in
the אמוראים Amoraim yesterday and it appears that they did not know
this ברייתא. Braita.
מכרה כתובתה, Machra kesuvata, she sold her כתובה. kesuvah. משכנה כתובתה, Mishkena
kesuvata, excuse me, she used her כתובה kesuvah as a collateral for
a loan. עשתה כתובתה אפותיקי לאחר, Asta kesuvata apotiki le'acher, or she
used her כתובה kesuvah as a I guess a different kind of
collateral. I'm not sure specifically what's the difference between אפותיקי apotiki and
a משכון. mashkon. Essentially an אפותיקי apotiki is something where you you
you say, when I pay you when when you come to be
paid back, you'll be paid back from this specific field or something
like that. אין לה מזונות. Ein lah mezonos. She doesn't have she
doesn't get מזונות. mezonos. Says the גמרא, Gemara, הני אין. Hani in.
These are the cases where a woman doesn't get מזונות. mezonos. It's
funny to do double negatives now. אבל תובעת לא. Aval tova'at lo.
But a woman who goes to בית דין Beit Din doesn't not
get מזונות, mezonos, meaning she should get מזונות. mezonos. So we say,
הני בין בבית דין בין שלא בבית דין. Hani bein beveit din
bein shelo beveit din. Those cases are a woman are cases where
a woman regardless of whether she's done it in some kind of
legal capacity or... outside of the בית דין, Beit Din, those cases
already indicate that she no longer has control of her כתובה, Ketubah,
presumably because she has used her כתובה Ketubah and essentially mortgaged it
to somebody else.
Whereas טובת, Tovat, טובת, Tovat,
a case of a woman who demands her actual כתובה, Ketubah, it's
not a matter of the fact that she's sort of given up
rights to her כתובה Ketubah and let somebody else have power over
it. The fact that she is now demanding it בבית דין אין,
Beveit Din in, if she's doing it in an official capacity, that's
enough to remove the the need of the מזונות. Mezonot. שלא בבית
דין לא, Shelo Beveit Din lo, but if she did it outside
of בית דין, Beit Din, she continues to receive מזונות. Mezonot.
Now these days where none of this, none of these לשונות Leshonot
are in our כתובות Ketubot anyway, does any of this change?
I presume that the
לשונות, Leshonot, you mean לשון Leshon of the תנאי בית דין? Tna'ei
Beit Din?
Yeah, I mean, I mean, you know, none of this is in
our כתובה Ketuba and I don't know that we sign this at
any point, you know.
I actually don't know the הלכה למעשה Halakha L'ma'aseh regarding תנאי בית
דין Tna'ei Beit Din in terms of who is responsible for for
the מזונות Mezonos and stuff like that. I think in normal cases,
I mean, I, you know, we go according to whatever the will
is of a husband. I don't even know in terms of the,
you know, how, how, in a divorce case, how, how payment of
the כתובה Ketuba works out with alimony and things like that in
terms of what we have in our in our secular culture. So
I can't speak to that directly. My expectation is that we generally
have,
we generally the תנאי כתובה Tna'ei Ketuba are not written, but they're
still in place and that we would, you would still follow the
last, the הלכה, Halakha, yes, Charlie.
I heard Rabbi Willig state in a שיעור shiur once that כתובות
Ketubas are basically completely unenforceable in the United States.
Okay, I mean, that doesn't mean that, I mean, unenforceable is not
the same thing as a בית דין, Beit Din, you know, like
somebody who wants to keep the הלכה, Halakha, and their family want
to keep the הלכה, Halakha, what do they do? That I don't
know. Yeah, it doesn't make, it doesn't surprise me to find out
that they're unenforceable in terms of a somebody who says, a woman
who says, okay, you owe me the money, you know, the כסף,
keses, the, you know, מאתן כסף Ma'atan Kessef that you promised me
and the guy says, well, you know, go whistle for it. I
can, I can understand that. Yeah, the question is what about people
who actually want to do, want to follow the הלכה? Halakha? Okay,
וכך היו אנשי ירושלים וכולי. Ve'khakh Hayu Anshei Yerushalayim v'khulei.
So now we get this really interesting discussion of the geographic locations.
If you recall in the משנה, Mishnah, אנשי ירושלים Anshei Yerushalayim ואנשי
הגליל v'Anshei HaGalil were holding basically according to the משנה, Mishnah, the
משנה Mishnah that says you can sit in my house all the
days that you are a widow, presumably until you get married. We've
learned that there's another thing that also comes in which is that
she actually demands her כתובה. Ketuba. That's also good enough to get
her out. The other says until my, until my יורשים, Yorshim, until
my heirs choose to to give you your כתובה Ketuba and then
they can send you out. So it's right a difference at least
of whose choice it is to give the כתובה. Ketuba. And if
the, if the heirs wish, they can pay off her כתובה Ketuba
right away and say okay, now you go support yourself. איתמר, Itmar,
רב אמר הלכה כאנשי יהודה ושמואל אמר הלכה כאנשי גליל. Rav Amar
Halakha Ke'anshei Yehuda U'shmuel Amar Halakha Ke'anshei Galil.
רב Rav said the הלכה Halakha is like the people who said
that the, it's up to the inheritors
to decide when to to give her her כתובה Ketuba and at
that point they can stop giving her מזונות. Mezonot. שמואל Shmuel said
no, it's like the משנה Mishnah that we saw that she can
sit in there in the house until she decides that she's ready
to leave,
you know, based on the other criteria that we've seen. בבל ובכל
פוודא נהוג כרב. Bavel Bekhol Pavadha Nahug KeRav.
בבל Bavel which is interesting, I think of בבל Bavel as the
entire geographic territory that we call בבל, Bavel, but it appears to
be referring to a particular city
called בבל Bavel and all of its
neighbors,
environs, suburbs and so on, hold like רב. Rav. נהרדעא ובכל פוודא
נהוג כשמואל. Naharda Bekhol Pavadha Nahug KeShmuel.
But the area of נהרדעא, Naharda, which I would have said is
in בבל, Bavel, holds like שמואל. Shmuel.
What's בבל Bavel there in the English? What's בבל Bavel as the
name
of a city also?
Babylon? Yes, I guess I I had the feeling that the city
of בבל Bavel is, the בבל Bavel was originally a city-state which
then became the empire of that city-state,
but I was, I've never, you don't see so-and-so from בבל Bavel
meaning from a particular town. Yeah, it was abandoned at that point,
it was abandoned.
Oh, so that's interesting. So it's an abandoned city held like him,
what's that mean?
It seems to be a geographic, a way of identifying the geographical
location.
The entire region. Yeah. But doesn't... but doesn't include one city in
there, I don't
know.
You know, the תוספות Tosafot in ש"ס Shas says when the גמרא
Gemara says in בבל Bavel הלכה כרב, halacha keRav, it referred to
the other parts of בבל Bavel not to נהרדעא Nehardea and סורא
Sura and the surrounding
cities.
Okay, so it's a slight—whether whatever they meant, it's an odd way
of saying it regardless. In any case, האי בת מחוזא דהוות נסיבה
לנהרדעא. hai bat Mechoza dehavat neseiva l'Nehardea. So there was a woman
who came from מחוזא. Mechoza. מחוזא Mechoza apparently is in the area
of בבל וכל פרודה, Bavel vechol parvadah, and she got married to
somebody who was from
נהרדעא. Nehardea. Now the whole process happens, right? Her husband dies and
now she wants to get מזונות, mezonot, and the question is how
long can she continue to get
מזונות. mezonot. אתו לקמיה דרב... דרב נחמן. atu lekamei d'Rav... d'Rav Nachman.
They came to רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. שמע לקלה דבת מחוזא היא.
shama l'kala d'bat Mechoza hi. He heard from the way she was
talking, from her accent, that she was from
מחוזא. Mechoza. אמר להו: בבל וכל פרודה נהוג כרב. amar lehu: Bavel
vechol parvadah nahug keRav. The מנהג minhag in her area is to
hold like רב, Rav, which is to say that the הלכה halacha
is כאנשי יהודה, ke'anshei Yehuda,
which means that the heirs can send her off early.
אמרו ליה, amru lei, they said back to him, והא לנהרדעא נסיבה,
veha l'Nehardea neseiva, she was married to someone from נהרדעא. Nehardea. אמר
להו: אי הכי, נהרדעא וכל פרודה נהוג כשמואל. amar lehu: ee hachi,
Nehardea vechol parvadah nahug keShmuel. If that's the case, then נהרדעא Nehardea
holds like שמואל, Shmuel, and it appears, and I think it's a
reasonable way to put it, that the husband's geographical origin seems to
be the determining position, which makes sense that he, because he's the
one who's actually writing his כתובה, ketubah, so his unstated תנאים tna'im
are likely to be based on his cultural understanding.
ועד היכא נהרדעא? ve'ad heicha Nehardea? So how far does נהרדעא Nehardea
stretch when you want to say, you know, נהרדעא וכל פרודה? Nehardea
vechol parvadah? עד היכא דסגי קבא דנהרדעא. ad heicha de-sagei kava de-Nehardea.
Every place where they use the נהרדעא Nehardean קבא, kav,
the unit of measurement, I guess it's a unit of volume, the
metric system for the city. Which is—yeah, I guess so, right—which is
the קבא. kav. נהרדעא Nehardea had a specific קבא, kav, and that's
how far—you always know that you're in the נהרדעא Nehardean vicinity when
they're using that unit of measurement.
איתמר. itmar. אלמנה: רב אמר שמין מה שעליה ושמואל אמר אין שמין
מה שעליה. almenah: Rav amar shamin ma she'aleha veShmuel amar ein shamim
ma she'aleha. When a widow goes in to finally get her כתובה,
ketubah, do we count the clothes on her back or do we
not count the clothes on her back based
on—doesn't he have to give her that anyway, like shirts or something?
Yes, but now he's dead. What happens if, in the course of
the time, she has now taken other clothes?
You mean these are new clothes, not the clothes she had when
she was still married to the guy?
Presumably so, although you wonder who those clothes actually belong to. If
he's providing her with כסות, ksut, does that כסות ksut belong to
her or does that כסות ksut belong to him that he provides
her with? I'm not sure the answer is.
So it seems like, you know, but that seems like something someone
should have said, like, you know, okay, I'll give you כסות, ksut,
but you know, just remember every single pair of shoes I'm keeping
tally with and I'll give you less, you know, if this marriage
ends.
Well, so it seems to be a מחלוקת machloket between רב Rav
and
שמואל. Shmuel. אמר רב חייא בר אבין: ובחילופא בלקט. amar Rav Chiya
bar Avin: u'vechilufa belakit. And the opposite is true of somebody who
is a hired worker. A hired worker, we say
that רב Rav would have said
we don't count whatever he's wearing that he received from the employer,
and שמואל Shmuel says we do count when the time comes to
pay him his wages.
רב כהנא מתני—meaning
Rav
Kahana
matnei like what, if he has to wear a uniform?
No, presumably that he's living—it's a—he's a hired worker, so he's, you
know, he's working a season in somebody's field and that person also
provides him with his various needs. When the time comes for him
to come and collect his wages, the question is: do you start
calculating, okay, you used this equipment that I gave you, these clothes,
what you're wearing is clothes that I gave you in order to
do the work and that comes out of your salary? It's interesting;
it reminds me of
Grapes of Wrath, company store. Why would they be reversed? So I
assume that what we're talking about is what is the
assumption that one has. One could say, I mean, and go in
both directions, with a wife one could say either that you expect
that anything she takes, especially after the husband is dead, starts to
accumulate against her כתובה, ketubah, particularly things that don't fall under the
category of מזונות, mezonot,
whereas by a worker, right, you would say no, everything he takes
is simply for the purpose of doing his job and his salary
was קבוע *kavua* from from before, right, not including things that he
took. Or you could say, no, a woman is entitled to certain
things while she's there, whereas this guy, he has a salary, the
stuff that he takes in the meantime, those are expenses that he
incurs and they are at his
expense. I don't know if there's a specific connection to רב Rav
*Rav* or שמואל Shmuel, *Shmuel* for each of those, but you can
understand that somebody might hold differently
for a worker
or for a wife.
In any case, we also have someone who says, hold on a
second... right, רב כהנא מתני וכן
בלקית *Rav Kahana matni v'chen b'lakit*. רב כהנא *Rav Kahana* would held
that actually there was the same מחלוקת machloket *machloket* by a somebody
who had been working. ומנח בה סימנא
*U'manach bah simana*, and he gave it a סימן siman *siman* to
remember, יתמא yatma. ועלמא וארמלתא שלח ופוק shlach ufok *Yatma v'alma v'almaltah
shlach u'fok*. A little hard-hearted I would say, but
an orphan and a widow, take off your clothes and get out.
That is presumably according to the שיטה *shita* of רב *Rav*. אמר
רב נחמן
*Amar Rav Nahman*: אף על גב דתנן במתניתין כוותיה דשמואל הלכתא כוותיה
דרב *Af al gav d'tnan b'matnitin k'vatei d'Shmuel hilchata k'vatei d'Rav*. Even
though we have a ברייתא *braita* that says according to שמואל *Shmuel*,
we still hold that the הלכה halacha *halacha* is like רב *Rav*.
דתנן *Detnan*,
sorry,
it's a משנה Mishna *mishna*. דתנן *Detnan*: אחד המקדיש נכסיו ואחד המעריך
את עצמו אין לו בכסות אשתו ולא בכסות בניו ולא בצבע שצבע
לשמן ולא בסנדלים חדשים שלקח לשמן *Echad hamakdish nechasav v'echad hamaarich et
atzmo ein lo b'ksut ishto v'lo b'ksut banav v'lo b'tzeva shetzava lishmon
v'lo b'sandalin chadashim shelekach lishmon*. So this is what Michael
said. Anybody who says who makes his everything that he owns הקדש
*hekdesh*, or he makes his own value הקדש *hekdesh*, so he makes
a נדר *neder* on himself, doesn't count up when he's calculating out
his net worth, doesn't count up the clothes that he's given to
his wife and children, nor different kinds of dyes that he's purchased
for them, nor new shoes that he's purchased for them. Meaning that
apparently those things belong to them, they don't belong to him
anymore. So that would suggest that if those things belong to them,
then you shouldn't be taking them out of the כתובה ketubah *ketubah*.
אמר ליה רבא לרב נחמן *Amar lei Rava l'Rav Nahman*: וכי מאחר
דתנן מתניתין כוותיה דשמואל אמאי הלכתא כוותיה דרב *V'chi me'achar d'tnan matnitin
k'vatei d'Shmuel amai hilchata k'vatei d'Rav*? If the משנה Mishna *mishna* says
like שמואל *Shmuel*, why are you פסקנ *paskening* הלכה *halacha* like רב
*Rav*? That doesn't make sense. אמר ליה *Amar lei*: לכאורה כשמואל רהיטא
כי מעיינת בה הלכתא כוותיה דרב *L'ichora k'Shmuel rahita ki maayant bah
hilchata k'vatei d'Rav*. It starts out if you think of it just
at a shallow level then it does appear to be like שמואל
*Shmuel*. However, if you look at it more deeply you can understand
that the הלכה *halacha* is actually like רב *Rav*. מאי טעמא *Mai
taama*, what's the reason? כי אקני לה אדעתא דמיקם קמיה אדעתא דמיקם
ולמיפק לא אקני לה *Ki aknei lah adata d'meikam kamei adata d'meikam
u'lmeifak la aknei lah*. The purpose of buying it was that they
would exist in front of him. He would continue to be, he
would see his wife wearing the clothing he gave her. He would
see his children wearing the new shoes that he got them. But
on the with the possibility that they would take those valuables and
leave his house, that isn't, that's not why he bought them. This
just goes back to a theme in this chapter. I'm not sure,
you can tell me probably better, I haven't learned מסכת masechet, כתובות
*masechet Ketubot* for a long time, if it's a theme in the
מסכת *masechet*, but a theme in at least in this chapter, that
as much as possible בית דין beit din *Beit Din* is trying
to do a kind of אומדנא דעת *umden dat* on the what
a person means when they write something, what a person expects. If
you recall, I mean the clearest case to me is the case
if you recall about the person who goes crazy, in which case
we continue to give מזונות mezonot *mezonot* to his wife, as opposed
to a person who abandons his wife and children, or sorry, feed
his children, whereas a person who abandons his wife and children we
don't give מזונות mezonot *mezonot* to the children. And the answer seems
to be that well we assume that if he abandoned them, he
didn't have the intention of actually taking care of them, whereas somebody
who goes crazy our general assumption is that he doesn't. Anyways, this
fits into that pattern very nicely.
But it doesn't necessarily answer the question of, you know, what if
it was stuff that they had while he was alive and he
dies? You know what I mean?
They were wearing it in front of him. From the way we
learn
this, okay, it appears to me that we are talking about things
that he gave them in his lifetime, based on the משנה Mishna
*mishna*, and the answer would be yes, but he... He never intended
for it to be something that they would take out of his
property. He never intended it not to be something that would go
to his יורשים or something like that.
Yeah, you could make an argument that this statement would apply only
in the case of divorce and not in the case of his
predeceasing.
Yes, it sounds like
you could make that argument without violating the logic behind it.
That's right. That's right. Yes, David.
These rulings seem to,
this idea that תורה Torah is constantly saying how careful you should
be with the widow and the orphan and here they are actually
putting it in the context of calling that worker an orphan. You
know, the worker an orphan, so you have the actual phrase widow
and orphan and it seems a little strange that, I don't know,
you know, I mean
I would just to add to what you're saying I would say
the לשון lashon of
יתמא ואלמנא
yatma ve'almana פוק pok שלח ופוק
is a, right, take off your clothes and get out, that's a
very kind of deeply ironic statement.
Nobody challenges it and there are plenty of places...
Well it's a סימן siman that statement. It's not a... even so.
Yes, it is, it's surprising that there's not, I mean on one
hand we're in a world of protections for the יתום ואלמנה yatom
ve'almana and you have to also remember that the place that we
are is a place that pits the יתום yatom against the אלמנה.
almana. The אלמנה almana is taking resources from the יתומים, yetomim, the
יתומים yetomim are attempting to hold on to their resources while also
expressing some kind of responsibility towards a woman who may actually not
be related to them.
And the יתומים yetomim may now also be קטנים. ketanim. You know,
all of these things you know.
Right, when I mentioned the word orphan
I was talking about the worker. Oh, the worker that they talked
about here, that's why they call him an orphan, yeah. So rather
than the orphans of the, I wasn't
referring to the orphans of the slave.
Oh, okay, that may
be a note here but anyway that was the context that I,
oh that they understand when it says יתמא ואלמלתא yatma ve'almata to
understand that to be referring to the worker?
It says, "And the orphan and the widow let them strip off
their clothing,"
right?
I also thought that myself, that they were the worker, the orphan,
so it's a statement about the worker.
That's odd though that you would, I mean it's odd to make
that a
סימן because it refers to the worker having the
uniform...
No, it makes sense to me, I just don't understand why they're
calling the worker the יתמא. yatma, I don't know why.
Does it say they have a reference for that?
רש"י Rashi says יתמא, לקיט, lakit, רש"י Rashi says it.
Yes, that's right, רש"י Rashi says it. I don't understand why, I
mean it's a strange...
it says because for him being sent away without clothing he is
accorded orphan's treatment.
Okay.
All right.
This is an interesting story.
Oh, and I didn't get to this story yet. Oh yeah we
did. כלתא דבי רב בר אלישיב הוה כתבא כתובתה מיתמי.
kaltah devei Rav Bar Eliyashiv havah katvah
ketubtah miyatmei. A widow from the house of Rav Bar Eliyashiv was
demanding her כתובה ketubah? from the
orphans. הוה קמיטמטלו לבי דינא havah kamitmatlu levei dina and she summoned
them to בית דין beit din to make it
official. They said זילא לן מילתא דתיזלי הכי. zila lan milta detizli
hachi.
It is embarrassing for us for you to go out in such
poor
attire. So who said this? The יתמי yatmei said to
her, it's uncomfortable for us to see you, you know, for you
to go out you know dressed poorly, you should you know dress
up for this. You're going to בית bet דין din for goodness
sake. אזלה לבישתינהו ואכסתינהו לכולהו מאנה. azlah levishatinhu ve'ichasatinhu lechulhu manei. She
went out and she put on all of her best clothes and
all of her most expensive jewelry. Great idea. They went in front
of רבינא. Ravina. He said to them, הלכתא כוותיה דרב דאמר אלמנה
שמינן מה שעליה. hilchata kevateih deRav de'amar almana shaminin mah she'aleha. He
said the הלכה is like Rav who says that you calculate what
the widow is wearing. Does she just, I mean it doesn't mean
what she's wearing that second, right? It means what she has in
her wardrobe, or just that day?
You mean she has like the
rest of her clothes are held against her?
So I think the expectation at least here is what she's got
on her right now. What she doesn't have on her doesn't come
out of her... apparently not. Yes, Charlie? Isn't it unusual that we
rule like Rav
in his dispute over financial matters?
So two
in a
row. Hold on
one second.
So we have, I mean the reason is because he interprets this
משנה mishnah according to Rav. Even though the משנה mishnah sounds like
it's like שמואל, I don't know, it's still odd that we would
hold. So usually we would hold according to רב in the when,
right? In any story. Yes, that's true. Yeah, it's unusual. I was
thinking the same thing as
both
the marriage proposal. Can't the orphans set up some guy to propose
to her and stuff like that?
That's the same kind of trickery or ruse that's sort of going
on here.
Yes,
you
can imagine such shenanigans
taking place. It is possible that you don't have every protection. And
when women need to learn גמרא. Gemara. I mean that is in
fact the מחלוקת machloket in the place where it says כל המלמד
בתו תורה מלמדה תפלות,
kol hamelamed
beto
Torah melamda tiflut, that in that discussion the reason that
the previous
position is you need to teach your daughter תורה Torah because she
needs to understand all of these הלכות halachot so she doesn't end
up in a situation like this. And the answer is yes, but
if she understands then she'll be able to circumvent it and she'll
be
able to take advantage of her. So I understand, all I'm saying
is that your position is an accepted I mean that is exactly
one of the reasons
that we say that women should learn תורה. Torah. Okay. ההוא דאמר
להו Ha-hu de-amar le-hu
נדוניא לברתיה. nidunya le-varta.
Somebody who said I want you to give my daughter the following
dowry. And then he passes away. זל נדוניא. zal nidunya. What happens
if he doesn't give a monetary number, he gives
a certain amount of
or let's say this, he says give the standard dowry to my
daughter and the standard dowry goes
down. אמר רב אידי בר אבין amar Rav Idi bar Avin פורנא
ליתמי. purna leyatme. The יתמי yatme take the extra money. In other
words, you pay her the lower dowry
and the יתמי yatme gain. ההוא דאמר להו ha-hu de-amar le-hu if
there's a man who says
ארבע מאה זוזי מן חמרא לברתיה, arba mea zuzei min hamra le-varta,
I want you to give 400 זוז zuz worth of wine
to my daughter as her
dowry. איקר חמרא, aykar hamra, wine then goes up in price so
she ends up getting less wine if you count by
present
standards.
אמר רב יוסף. amar Rav Yosef.
Base value, different quantity? Right. אמר
רב יוסף amar Rav Yosef רווחא ליתמי. revacha leyatme. The יתמי yatme
are the gainers. In other words, they end up keeping the wine.
Another case of relatives of
רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. קריביה דרבי יוחנן
krivei de-Rabbi Yochanan הוה להו איתת אבא דהוה קמפסדה מזוני.
havo le-hu itat abba de-hava
kamifseda mezonei.
The relatives of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan if you recall the last
time the relatives of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan approached him he gave
them some advice which apparently worked but then he regretted it. This
time they have a stepmother who is just going through
their father's goods
like a house on fire. The father's still alive by the way.
But she is apparently just spending money left and right and they're
afraid for their
inheritance. אתו לקמיה דרבי יוחנן. atu lekamei de-Rabbi Yochanan. They came to
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan for advice. אמר להו amar le-hu apparently he
didn't take his own advice about
not giving advice to your relatives when you're אדם חשוב adam chashuv
because he has new advice for
them. איזילו ואמרו לאבוכון דניחד לה ארעא למזוני. izilu ve-imru le-avuchon de-nyached
la ara le-mezonei. Tell your father to specify a particular field which
is going to come
her sustenance and once she goes through that it's all over.
This is not for the כתובה?
ketubah No. Okay. This is at present. אתו לקמיה דריש לקיש. atu
lekamei de-Resh Lakish. So then the time came, she apparently went through
it. They went to ריש לקיש. Resh Lakish. אמר להו amar le-hu
כל שכן שריבה לה מזוני. kol she-ken she-riba la mezonei. All the
more so I'm sorry it must be for the כתובה ketubah. because
then their father dies and now she's demanding she has only this
one field which is supposed to her מזונות mezonot, are supposed to
come out of that. Which are not the כתובה. ketubah. It is
the כתובה.
ketubah That's what you said, we had that specific משנה that if
you say that I want you to
give this one field it's not valid because all your נכסים nechasim
are משועבדים meshubadim for the mammon time. But for מזונות mezonot apparently
not at least according to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, ריש לקיש Resh
Lakish disagrees. They come to Reish Lakish now, she's demanding more than
what they offer. They say the father gave, he gave this field
for your מזונות, mezonot, this is how much you
get. And Reish Lakish says כל שכן שבא למזונות. kol sheken sheba
la-mezonot. All the more so, right? Okay, he added on this field
that you know, you would have had the field, but now he
says besides the מזונות mezonot. that you're giving her, you also owe
her this field. אמרו ליה והא רבי יוחנן לא אמר הכי. Amru
lei ve-ha Rabbi Yochanan lo amar hachi. They said to him, wait
a minute, this is advice that came straight from
רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. אמר להו זילו הבו לה ואי לא מפיקנא
לכו רבי יוחנן מאונייכו. Amar lehu zilu havu lah ve-ee la mapfiekna
lechu Rabbi Yochanan mi-onaichu.
Go and pay her what you owe her, and if
you don't, I'll take רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan right out of your
ear. Reish Lakish, at least according to the אגדה, aggadah, was
a—had a history of
violence, and I can imagine that if he threatened you, it wouldn't
have been
pleasant. אתו לקמיה דרבי יוחנן, Atu le-kamei de-Rabbi Yochanan, they went to
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan to see if anything could be done. Of
course, he's נוגע בדבר, nogei'a ba-davar, he can't be the דיין, dayan,
but they say, what about this advice you gave us, this terrible
advice? אמר להו מה אעשה שכנבכי חלוק עלי. Amar lehu ma asseh
she-kenavchi chaluk alai. What can I do, people don't always agree with
me? אמר רבי אבהו לדידי מפרשא לי מיניה דרבי יוחנן. Amar Rabbi
Abahu le-didi mefarshei li minei de-Rabbi Yochanan. I know what רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan meant. This is what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan should have
said to
them. אמר למזונות ריבה. Amar li-mezonot riba. If you say this field
is for מזונות, mezonot. then you've added on to what she receives
from
מזונות. mezonot. סליחה, selicha, למזונות ריבה למזונות. li-mezonot riba la-mezonot. That is
an additional מזונות. mezonot. אמר במזונות. Amar bi-mezonot. This field is your
מזונות. mezonot, קצץ למזונות. katzatz la-mezonot. Then you shorten the מזונות. mezonot,
And what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan told them to say was, go
to the father, this is רבי אבהו Rabbi Abahu trying to—told them
go to the father and say במזונות, bi-mezonot, that this field will
be your מזונות, mezonot. and instead he said this field will be
for your מזונות, meaning additional to your מזונות.
The difference between a למד lamed and a בית makes that much
difference?
Yes, it's a strong grammatical difference. הדרן לך נערה. Hadran lach na'ara.
Does anybody have the time? It's 11:45.
Okay,
we
should be able to—anyway, נ"ה Nun Hey is short, so Rabbi Levinson
shouldn't have any trouble catching up. אף על פי שאמרו בתולה גובה
מאתיים ואלמנה מנה. Af
al pi she-amru betulah
gova matayim ve-almanah maneh. This is actually a משנה that over the
course of the last פרק perek you've seen every part of this
משנה in various contexts. אף על פי שאמרו בתולה גובה מאתיים ואלמנה
מנה אם רצה להוסיף אפילו מאה מנה יוסיף. Af al pi she-amru
betulah gova matayim ve-almanah maneh, im ratzah le-hosif afilu me'ah maneh yosif.
Even though we say that a כתובה ketubah should get two hundred
and אלמנה almanah should get one hundred, if he wants to add
to that, he can add. נתאלמנה או נתגרשה בין מן האירוסין בין
מן הנישואין גובה את הכל. Nit'almanah oh nitgarsha bein min ha-eirusin bein
ha-nisu'in gova et ha-kol.
If she is widowed or divorced, whether or not from אירוסין, eirusin,
whether from נישואין, nisu'in, she receives—she can take all of it, meaning
both the two hundred and one hundred and the תוספת. tosefet. רבי
אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azariah says—by the way, in our—in
the last פרק perek when we read it, we interpreted it also
to be referring to the נדוניא. nedunya. רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi
Elazar ben Azariah says מן הנישואין גובה את הכל מן האירוסין בתולה
גובה מאתיים ואלמנה מנה. min ha-nisu'in gova et ha-kol min ha-eirusin betulah
gova matayim ve-almanah maneh.
If it's from נישואין, nisu'in, that's when she can start receiving תוספת,
tosefet, but if it's only from אירוסין, eirusin, she should only get
the official—the official amount that comes to her. שלא כתב לה אלא
על מנת לכונסה. she-lo katav lah ela al menat le-chochzah. Because he
didn't add to her, give her extra presents, except for on the
condition that he would actually get to marry her. רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda says אם רצה כותב לבתולה שטר של מאתיים והיא כותבת התקבלתי
ממך מנה ולאלמנה מנה והיא כותבת התקבלתי ממך חמישים. im ratzah kotev
le-betulah shtar shel matayim ve-hi kotevet hitkabalti mimcha maneh, ve-la-almanah maneh ve-hi
kotevet hitkabalti mimcha chamishim. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says if she wants,
she can—he writes to her a כתובה ketubah. of two hundred and
she can write him a receipt saying I've received one hundred. Note,
even if she hasn't received the one hundred. This is a way
of her defraying the costs of marriage for her husband or something.
And therefore we can say that she can—he can get away with
giving her less than the two hundred. And
in אלמנה, almanah, he writes her for one hundred and she writes
I've received fifty.
Why would she agree to do that?
I presume for the reason I just said, that she—they want to
get married, the man doesn't have the kind of money he would
need in order to have an official כתובה.
ketubah So she's basically giving
her—giving him—it's a kind of מחילה. mechilah.
Yeah.
She's forgiving him that amount.
Right. If you—if you recall, we discussed—so רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says
כל הפוחת לבתולה ממאתיים ולאלמנה ממנה הרי זו בעילת זנות. kol ha-pocheit
li-betulah mi-matayim ve-la-almanah mi-maneh harei zo be'ilat zenut. Anybody who gives less
than two hundred to a בתולה betulah or less than one hundred
to an אלמנה, almanah, that's בעילת זנות. be'ilat zenut. And it appears
that he's in מחלוקת with רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda here. If you
recall when we interpreted it back then...
it sounded like רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* doesn't have to be understood
as פוחת *pochet* because he actually does write the 200, so you
don't have to understand a מחלוקת *machloket* between רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*
and רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* here, but it does appear that they
are in מחלוקת *machloket*. Yes, גמרא *Gemara*. פשיטא *Pshita*. It's obvious if
he wants to add, of course he can add, you can give
money to whoever you want. I can go out and add money
to whatever I owe, you know, if I go to Starbucks I
could pay with a 100 dollar bill and say keep the change.
מהו דתימא *mahu deteyma*, what's the, why are we, what would we
have thought? קצבתא עבדו רבנן שלא לבייש את מי שאין לו קמשמע
לן *kitzuta avdu rabanan shelo levayesh et mi she'en lo kamashma lan*.
The Rabbis determined that there is only a certain amount that you're
permitted to give to a, to your wife, in order that people
won't be ashamed that they can't give as much. We've seen this
in various cases, the case of, and the most famous case is
the case of רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel* and the תכריכין *tachrichin*, that
the Rabbis are concerned that you're going to embarrass people. אם רצה
להוסיף וכולי קמשמע לן *im ratza lehosif vechulei kamashma lan* that yes,
you can give as much as you want. אם רצה להוסיף וכולי
*im ratza lehosif vechulei*. רצה לכתוב לה לא קתני *ratza lichtov la
lo katani*, it doesn't say if he wants to write her more
money he can write her, אלא רצה להוסיף *ela ratza lehosif*, but
rather it says if he wants to add to the כתובה ketubah
*ktuba*. מסייע ליה לרבי איבו אמר רבי ינאי דאמר רבי איבו אמר
רבי ינאי תנאי כתובה ketubah. ככתובה דמי *mesaye lei le'Rabbi Ibo amar
Rabbi Yannai de'amar Rabbi Ibo amar Rabbi Yannai tnai ktuba ke'ktuba damei*.
So this supports the position that the תנאי כתובה ketubah. *tnai ktuba*,
the additional things that you add on to the כתובה ketubah, *ktuba*,
including the תנאי כתובה ketubah. *tnai ktuba* we talked about before, including
the תוספת tosefet *tosefet*, all of them are actually become a part
of the כתובה ketubah. *ktuba* and they fit. נפקא מינה *nafka mina*.
How do you say your ktuba is 300, rather he says your
ktuba is 200 and I'm adding on another 100, that's what it's
saying right?
It's the opposite, in other words, it's saying you might think that
it's like an extra gift, and he's saying no, your כתובה ketubah.
*ktuba* is now whatever, 300, 400. נפקא מינה *nafka mina* and then
we have a נפקא מינה *nafka mina* for a variety of things:
למוכרת *le'mocheret*, if she sells her כתובה ketubah, *ktuba* now she doesn't
get any of the things including the תוספת tosefet *tosefet*. למוכרת *le'mocheret*,
if she says I'm מוכרת *mocheret* on my כתובה *ktuba*, the תוספת
tosefet *tosefet* also goes. למורדת *le'moredet*,
if she has done one of the things that we reduce her
כתובה *ktuba*, we don't just reduce the 200 or the 100 but
the תוספת *tosefet* stays in place, we start with the תוספת *tosefet*
and we start reducing from there and she can reduce all the
way down to zero. לפוגמת *le'fogemet*, a woman who claims who has
received part of her כתובה *ktuba* and has written a receipt for
part of it, has to recollect the rest with a שבועה shvuah.
*shvua*. Well, what if she's only collected part of the תוספת *tosefet*?
The answer is the תוספת *tosefet* is just like the כתובה *ktuba*,
she still needs to take a שבועה shvuah *shvua*.
How do you see this from the terminology, ratza lehosif, I don't
understand that?
רצה להוסיף *ratza lehosif* instead of רצה לכתוב *ratza lichtov*. רש״י *Rashi*
says as follows: רצה לכתוב לא קתני אי תנא לכתוב להווה אמינא
מינה דלא יהא התוספת קרוי כתובה *ratza lichtov lo katani i tana
lichtov lahava amina mina dela yehei hatosefet karui ktuba*. If it had
said he wants to write, we would have understood that the תוספת
*tosefet* is not considered part of the כתובה *ktuba*, אלא כמתנה מדעתו
*ela kematana mida'ato*, rather it's a מתנה מדעתו *matana mida'ato*. He's writing
her something extra. להוסיף *lehosif* means he is adding to the actual
כתובה *ktuba*, as opposed to לכתוב לה *lichtov la*, which means a
separate clause that has its own legal situation. ואין שם כתובה עליו
*ve'ein shem ktuba alav* says רש״י *Rashi*. השתא דתנן להוסיף משמע נוסף
על הכתובה שתיקנו חכמים ושם כתובה עליו *hashta detnan lehosif mashma nosaf
al haktuba shetiknu chachamim veshem ktuba alav*. Because it's להוסיף על הכתובה
*lehosif al haktuba*, גם הוא מסייע ליה וכולי *gam hu mesaye lei
vechulei*. We'll just finish these last few. תובעת *tova'at*, a woman who
demands her כתובה *ktuba*, so if she demands the תוספת *tosefet*, that's
good enough to get rid of her מזונות *mezonot* that we just
talked about. לעוברת על דת *le'overet al dat*, a woman who does
one of a variety of things which you'll learn in two פרקים
*prakim* can be a divorce without a כתובה *ktuba*, and we say
that includes תוספת *tosefet*, she won't receive the תוספת *tosefet* either. לשבח
*leshevach*, if the כתובה *ktuba* goes up in
price... hold on a second...
right, if the כתובה *ktuba* goes up in price, does she get
the same 200?
Is this improvement to the property?
I'll read רש״י *Rashi* and it'll maybe, so it says as follows:
אינו בכלל נוטל פי שנים בשבח ששבחו הנכסים לאחר מיתת אביהם *eino
bechol notel pi shnayim beshevach sheshavchu hanechasim le'achar mitat avihem*. The first
sons do not receive
the double of the increase in the value of the property that
they inherit if it's increased after the father's death. ולא האישה בכתובתה
*velo ha'isha biktuvtah*. If the father dies and then whatever has been
laid aside from the כתובה *ktuba* increases in price, she only gets
the value of what it was at the time of the father's
death, and that includes the תוספת *tosefet*.
לשבועה, for collecting her כתובה from יתומים, yetomim, and there are cases
where עד אחד ed echad in מסכת שבועות masechet shevuot and other
things, where she have to collect with a שבועה. רש"י Rashi explains
why it says both שבועה and פוגמת. pogemet.
לשביעית, Lishvi'it, a כתובה is not, doesn't get annulled during שמיטה,
shmitah, which other kinds of debts do get annulled, and תוספת counts
for that.
ולכתוב כל נכסיו לבניו, Velichtov kol nechasav levanav, somebody who's written everything
he owns to his children, so אבדה כתובתה ibda ketuvta is the
rule. Somebody who writes all of his his his
lands to his children, apparently that's good enough to get rid of
the כתובה.
I thought all of his נכסים nechasim
are משועבדים meshubadim for a כתובה. How can? So it appears, yeah,
I'm not sure. I'm also not sure, but that seems to be
the case here. It's a סוגיה, sugya, I believe, that's going to
be in this מסכת, you'll come up to it. No, it's in
בבא בתרא קל"ב. Bava Batra kuf-lamed-bet. You're going to have to wait
for a couple of months.
לגבות מן הקרקע, Ligvot min hakarka, that it needs to be collected
from קרקע karka the same way as a כתובה, ומן הזיבורית umin
haziborit and it gets collected from the זיבורית, ziborit, ולכתובת בנין דכרין,
ulechtuvat benin dichrin, and for וכל זמן שהיא בבית אביה.
vechol zman shehi beveit aviah.
One more second. וכל זמן שהיא בבית אביה
בעלה במשך המוטן גובה כתובתה לעולם וכל זמן שהיא בבית אביה שלא
היו עובדים אותה
היתומים ולא זנין אותה גובה כתובתה.
Vechol zman shehi beveit aviah baala bemeshech hamutan gova ketuvtah leolam vechol
zman shehi beveit aviah shelo hayu ovdim otah hayetomim velo zanin otah
gova ketuvtah.
So there's a certain a certain amount of time if she's in
בית אביה beit aviah that she can collect. Twenty-five, after twenty-five years
she no longer collects, and that's true of the תוספת as well.
ולכתובת בנין דכרין, Ulechtuvat benin dichrin, and that also goes to her
to the כתובת בנין דכרין, ketuvat benin dichrin, to the sons. That's
it. Right,
these four things are inside, right? These are things where תוספת has
the דין of כתובה. Right. And so sometimes they're for things she'll
get more, sometimes she loses more depending on the case.
We also spoke about תוספת ובניה ודנותם שזה. tosefet uvaneha udenotam shezeh.
He noted pointing out that this is a short piece of רש"י
Rashi placed there that if one writes all his properties to his
sons and assigns to his wife a piece of land of any
size, she forfeits her כתובה.
So that second part: he writes
everything and this piece of קרקע. karka.
ובכתב לה קרקע כל שהוא.
Uvechotov lah karka
kol shehu.
Right, that's what רש"י Rashi says. ובכתב לה קרקע כל שהוא אבדה
כתובתה. Uvechotov lah karka kol shehu ibda ketuvtah. Right.
Well, it's just a substitute for collecting the כתובה. He's dead, she's
able, there's a legal... But it's קרקע כל שהוא. karka kol shehu.
It's not the full כתובה, so it's odd that he's able to
do it. The סוגיה sugya appears in בבא בתרא. Bava Batra.